A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, History, RG 12 FA1806
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, History, RG 12
1937-2016
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation
FA1806
1.9 Cubic Feet (5 containers)
Arrangement
As received.
Scope and Contents
Record Group 12 contains information related to the Knight Foundation history project. It contains the final version of "The Knight Foundation History" by Virginia Henke. Also included are photographs, clippings, and transcripts of the oral history interviews that were used to write the history.
Conditions Governing Access
Material less than 10 years old is restricted.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Oral history -- Interviews
- History, 1937-2012; 1; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document boxes
  - Policies and History, 1971 August 5-1991 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Knight File Number - 1951
    Scope and Contents
    Contains a collection of memos, correspondence, and policy statements concerning grants and giving. Includes memos from: John S. Knight appointing a journalism grant review committee, August 5, 1971; Lee Hills re: Future of the Knight Foundation, August 22, 1972; John S. Knight re: payout requirements, January 4, 1977; C.C. Gibson re: the first meeting of the Policy Review Committee, October 18, 1985; and Creed Black re: maintaining distinctions between the Knight Foundation and the Knight-Ridder newspaper chain. Also included is a "confidential statement of information about the Foundation" prepared by C.C. Gibson, February 24, 1978; a grants summary for the years 1982 - 1987; and a letter to the trustees of The Knight Foundation from James L. Knight outlining his vision for the future, April 6, 1990.
  - "Knight Foundation History", 1998 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    Knight File Number - 1618
    Knight Foundation History, written by Virginia Henke. 335 pages, including an appendix of original documents, and chronological lists of officers and trustees (1950-1998) and historical highlights (1950-1998). 1 bound copy, 1 unbound copy.
  - Knight Foundation - General History, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 2650
    Miscellaneous materials, including two documents with information culled from the Board minutes; background information on the Foundation prepared by CC Gibson; an article from the Foundation Giving Watch newsletter; a letter from Creed Black to the Editor of the Akron Beacon Journal correcting its story on the Knight Foundation; a history of Knight Foundation written in 1991; and a list of trustees as of March 1994 and the years they were elected to the Board.
  - Miami Herald History and John S. Knight Photos, 1937-2012 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 5982
    "The Miami Herald: Writing and Making History" and "The Knight Brothers: Building a Legacy" published in Preservation Today by Dade Heritage Trust in 2012. Also includes copies of two White House letters; copies of Miami Herald photos of John S. and James L. Knight and various people including: Frank B. Shutts, George C. Marshall, Dwight Eisenhower, Richard Nixon, Harry Truman, Luis Munoz Marin, Nelson Rockefeller, Adlai Stevenson, Barry Goldwater,Eleanor Roosevelt, the Duke of Windsor, Hubert Humphrey, Ben Schneider, Alvah Chapman, Bernard Ridder, Lee Hills
  - Final Edition, Journalism according to Jack and Jim Knight, DVD, 2009 (Box 1)
    Knight File Number - 5983
    DVD documentary by Paul Jacoway of Paul R. Jacoway Productions of Akron, OH and Kathleen Endres, professor at University of Akron. Tells the sotry of the Knight family, the Beacon Journal and the rise and fall of Knight-Ridder. Copyright Paul Jacoway.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Open for research. Digital access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
- Oral History Interviews, 1978-2016; 2; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
  - Agreements for Oral History Interview Transcripts, 1997 February 15-March 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1066
    Agreements for the oral history interview transcripts created by Virginia Henke. Includes a blank agreement, and those signed by interviewee and Eugene Struckhoff.
  - Interview with Cesar Alvarez by Laurie Peterson, 2012 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5137
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's oral history interview with Cesar Alvarez on February 7, 2012 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, release agreement, and keyword index.
  - Interview with Jerry Austen, by Virginia Henke, 1996 August 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1096
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with W. Gerald "Jerry" Austen, M.D. on 8/25/96 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter, biographical information, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Jerry Austen, by Timothy Jacobson, 1997 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1977
    Transcript from Timothy Jacobson's oral history interview with W. Gerald "Jerry" Austen, M.D. on 7/15/97 in Boston, MA. Includes transcript, release agreement, and keyword index.
  - Interview with W. Gerald Austen by Laurie Peterson, 2009 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4571
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's oral history interview with W. Gerald "Jerry" Austen, M.D. on 6/23/09 in Boston, MA. Includes transcript, release agreement, and keyword index.
  - Interview with Creed Black, by Virginia Henke, 1997 February 11-21 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1098
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Creed C. Black on 2/11/97 and 2/21/97 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter with a list of attachments, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Creed Black, by Timothy Jacobson, 1997 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1097
    Transcript from Timothy Jacobson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Creed C. Black on 6/4/97 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, index and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Creed Black, by Laurie Peterson, 2006 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 3772
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Creed C. Black on 03/13/2006. Includes transcript, index, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Robert Briggs, by Laurie Peterson, 2014 June 24-July 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 5465
    Restricted - Open 2025
    Edited transcript from Laurie Peterson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Rob Briggs (last few minutes were via telephone). Includes transcript, index, interview questions, and authorization letter. All materials also can be found on the W drive - Archives and Records Management folder.
  - Interview with Del Brinkman, by Virginia Henke, 1997 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 1099
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Del Brinkman on 2/27/97 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Hodding Carter III, by Laurie Peterson, 2005 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 3378
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Hodding Carter III on 09/19/2005. Includes transcript, index, list of questions and authorization letter. NOTE: original audiotapes destroyed per authorization letter.
  - Interviews with Hodding Carter III by Andrew Cohen (Box 1)
  - Interview with Alvah Chapman, by Timothy Jacobson, 1997 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 1978
    Transcript from Timothy Jacobson's oral history interview with Alvah Chapman on 6/3/97. Includes transcript, release agreement, and keyword index.
  - Interview with Alvah Chapman, by Virginia Henke, 1996 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Knight File Number - 1100
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Alvah Chapman on 10/3/96 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter, biographical information and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Charles Clark, by Virginia Henke, 1996 August 21 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1101
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Charles Clark on 8/21/96. Includes transcript, advance letter with list of background materials, biographical information and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Charles Clark, by Timothy Jacobson, 1997 June 4 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1981
    Transcript from Timothy Jacobson's oral history interview with Charles Clark on 6/4/97. Includes transcript, release agreement and keyword index..
  - Interview with Mary Sue Coleman, by Laurie Peterson, 2012 February 10 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5045
    Edited transcript from Laurie Peterson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Mary Sue Coleman (via telephone). Includes transcript, index, interview questions, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Jill Ker Conway, by Timothy Jacobson, 1998 January 22 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1102
    Transcript from Timothy Jacobson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Jill Ker Conway on 1/22/98. Includes transcript and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Jill Ker Conway, by Laurie Peterson, 2005 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 3124
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Jill Ker Conway on 6/30/2005. Includes transcript, index, list of questions and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Marjorie Knight Crane, by Virginia Henke, 1996 September 4 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1103
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Marjorie Knight Crane on 9/4/96. Includes transcript, advance letter with a list of background materials provided, biographical information and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Timothy Crowe, by Virginia Henke, 1997 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1105
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Timothy Crowe on 2/19/97. Includes transcript, Attachments, Biographical Information and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Timothy Crowe, by Timothy Jacobson, 1997 June 3 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1104
    Transcript from Timothy Jacobson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Timothy Crowe on 6/3/97. Includes transcript, index and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Marc Fest, by Laurie Peterson, 2011 November 28 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 4988
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's oral history interview with Marc Fest on November 28, 2011 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, index, a list of questions, and authorization letter. This interview was done shortly before Fest's resignation from KF as Vice President of Communications.
  - Interview with William Friday, by Virginia Henke, 1998 January 12 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 1106
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with William Friday on 1/12/98 in Chapel Hill, NC. Includes transcript, Advance letter, Biographical Information, authorization letter, and Charlie Adams letter.
  - Interview with C.C. Gibson by Virginia Henke, 1996 June 18-24 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 1065
    Transcript and notes from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with C.C. Gibson in Akron, Ohio, 6/18/96 and 6/24/96. A copy of the transcript release form is included, as well as a letter written to Mr. Gibson outlining the issues he would be asked to discuss.
  - Interview with Jessica Goldfin, by Laurie Peterson, 2012 July 13 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 5241
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's oral history interview with Jessica Goldfin on July 13, 2012 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, index, a list of questions, and authorization letter. This interview was done shortly after Goldfin left KF for a job with MIT Media Lab.
  - Interview with Paul Grogan, by Laurie Peterson, 2012 February 23 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Knight File Number - 5087
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's oral history interview with Paul Grogan on February 23, 2012 in Boston, MA. Includes transcript, index, a list of questions, and authorization letter. This interview was done shortly before Grogan's retirement from the KF Board of Trustees.
  - Interview with Gordon Heffern, by Virginia Henke, 1996 June 28 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1107
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Gordon Heffern on 6/28/96 in Cocoa Beach, FL. Includes transcript, Advance letter, Biographical Information and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Larry Jinks, by Virginia Henke, 1996 November 22 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1108
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Larry Jinks on 11/22/96, in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, Advance letter with list of attachments, Biographical Information and authorization letter.
  - Interview with John S. Knight, by Dan Neuharth, 1978 October 24-2006 March 27 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 3701
    Transcript from Dan Neuharth's oral history interview with John S. Knight in Akron, Oh.. Includes an introduction by Dan Neuharth. While the interview focuses on Knight's career and the state of the newspaper business, the Knight Foundation is mentioned on page 7. Also included is an op-ed piece written by Neuharth and posted on USATODAY.com in which he recalls his interview with Knight.
  - Interview with Belinda Lawrence, by Laurie Peterson, 2013 April 12 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5364
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's oral history interview with Belinda Lawrence on April 12, 2013 in Aventura, FL. Includes transcript, index, a list of questions, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Rick Love, by Virginia Henke, 1997 February 19 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1109
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Rick Love on 2/19/97, in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Penelope McPhee, by Virginia Henke, 1997 March 19-April 8 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1110
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Penelope McPhee on 3/19/97 and 4/8/97, in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter with a list of attachments, biographical information, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Penelope McPhee, by Laurie Peterson, 2004 March 22 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 2876
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's oral history interview with Penelope McPhee on 3/22/04, in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, a list of questions, biographical information, and authorization letter. This interview, done shortly before McPhee left Knight to head the Arthur M. Blank Family Foundation, picks up with McPhee's career in 1997. See Henke's earlier interview with McPhee for pre-1997 information.
  - Interview with Larry Meyer, by Laurie Peterson, 2008 July 9-11 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 4363
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's oral history interview with Larry Meyer on July 9 & 11, 2008, in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, index, a list of questions, and authorization letter. This interview was done shortly before Meyer's retirement from KF as Vice President of Communications and Secretary.
  - Interview with Rolfe Neill, by Timothy Jacobson, 1998 January 26 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1982
    Transcript from Timothy Jacobson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Rolfe Neill on 1/26/98. Includes transcript, keyword index, and release agreement.
  - Interview with Rolfe Neill by Laurie Peterson, 2012 October 22-November 7 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 5138
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's interview with Rolfe Neill, retired trustee. Also includes keyword index and release form.
  - Notes of Virginia Henke's interview with Lyle Nelson, 12/5/96, 1996 December 5 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 1149
    Notes and a detailed summary of Virginia Henke's interview with Lyle Nelson, conducted on 12/5/96 in Palo Alto, CA. No transcript of this interview was made, only a summary.
  - Interview with Eric Newton by Laurie Peterson, 2015 June 24-July 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 5697
    Restricted - Open 2026
    Edited transcript from Laurie Peterson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Eric Newton. Includes transcript, index, and release form.
  - Interview with Mariam Noland, by Laurie Peterson, 2014 June 3 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Knight File Number - 5466
    Edited transcript from Laurie Peterson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Mariam Noland. Includes transcript, index, release form, and interview questions.
  - Interview with Beverly Knight Olson, by Virginia Henke, 1996 September 17 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1147
    Transcript of Virginia Henke's interview with Beverly Knight Olson, on 9/17/96 in Miami, FL. Includes advance letter, list of background materials, biographical information, authorization and an index.
  - Interview with Mayur Patel by Laurie Peterson, 2014 January 13 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5385
    Restricted - Please contact an RAC archivist for further information.
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's interview with Mayur Patel, former VP of Strategy and Assessment. Also includes keyword index and release form.
  - Interview with Susan Patterson, by Laurie Peterson, 2016 February 10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5770
    Restricted - Open 2027
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's oral history interview with Susan Patterson on February 10, 2016 in Charlotte, North Carolina. Includes transcript, index, a list of questions, and authorization letter. This interview was done shortly after Ms. Patterson's retirement from KF as Charlotte's Program Director.
  - Interview with Linda L. Raybin, by Virginia Henke, 1997 March 5 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1111
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Linda Raybin, on 3/5/97 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter, biographical information, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Nancy Rabin, by Virginia Henke, 1998 February 10 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1146
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Nancy Raybin, strategic planning consultant to the foundation, on 2/10/98, in Washington, DC. Includes transcript with attachments, advance letter, and authorization letter. In this interview, Raybin discusses the culture of Knight Foundation, its program officers, board members, and governance issues. She oversaw the writing of a strategic plan in 1991, and again in 1995.
  - Interview with John W. Rogers, Jr. by Laurie Peterson, 2014 January 8 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 5320
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's interview with John W. Rogers, retired trustee. Also includes keyword index and release form.
  - Interview with Dennis Scholl by Laurie Peterson, 2016 January 4 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 5698
    Transcript from Laurie Peterson's interview with Dennis Scholl, Vice-President/Arts. Also includes keyword index and release form.
  - Interview with James Spaniolo, by Virginia Henke, 1996 September 19 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1112
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with James Spaniolo on 9/19/96 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter, biographical information, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Henry King Stanford, by Timothy Jacobson, 1996 January 26 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1113
    Transcript from Timothy Jacobson's (of the Winthrop Group) oral history interview with Henry King Stanford on 1/26/98 in Americus, GA. Includes transcript, index, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Eugene Struckhoff, by Virginia Henke, 1996 March 22 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 1114
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Eugene Struckhoff on 3/22/96 in Miami, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter, role with Knight Foundation, and authorization letter.
  - Interview with Barbara Knight Toomey, by Virginia Henke, 1997 January 16 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 1115
    Transcript from Virginia Henke's oral history interview with Barbara Knight Toomey on 1/16/97 in Sanibel, FL. Includes transcript, advance letter with a list of attachments, biographical information, and authorization letter.
  - Index to the Oral History Interview Transcripts, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    Knight File Number - 1148
    Index of the Oral History interview transcripts conducted by Timothy Jacobson of the Winthrop Group and Virginia Henke between 1996 and 1998. The index lists keywords, the interviewee, the date of the interview, and the page number. 230 pages. (2 folders)
  - Index to the Oral History Interview Transcripts, 1996-1998 (Box 4)